[Music]
the main result yesterday was called the
pank H hope theorem and it said that the
index summed over all the equilibria was
equal to the oil characteristic you
remember
any Vector field on your
manifold you look at all equilibria look
at the indices at the equilibria some
some of some over them and you get this
oila characteristic which in our
treatment was simply the number of Zero
Dimensional cells minus number of one
dimensional cells plus the number of two
dimensional cells minus the one number
of three dimensional cells and so on
beta 0 minus beta 1 plus beta 2 minus
beta 3 and so alternating some of the
numbers of cells okay we call this the
left hand side call this the right hand
side and we remarked that you can use
this formula in two different ways um
you
can use this um
formula if you know the right hand side
you can get the information about the
left hand side
right and that means that um which way
does it go actually this is quite
interesting I think it goes this way so
if I use it to deduce the right hand
side from left hand side it means that
you know the um knowing the
equilibria of v um find
out the oil characteristic okay in some
sense you are saying that if you know
something about the dynamical system you
can get information about the
topology of the manifold you can also
use
it in this
direction knowing that right hand side
deduce something about the left hand
side and that means that knowing the um
oil
characteristic
um find out something about um
information on the equilibria
[Applause]
of of v in other words the knowledge of
topology constrains the behavior of a
dynamical system on that manifold okay
you can go in both directions so today
we shall first
do
that direction so from left hand side to
right hand
side okay in other words we'll try to
find out the topology more concretely
the oiler characteristic of manifold by
looking at some dynamical systems Vector
fields on that
manifold a few examples
then let's
take begin with a sphere S2
we already know the oiler characteristic
he or Kai as Hamid would say um of this
manifold what was the other
characteristic hey hey what's the other
characteristic depending on the
dimension of the sphere it was one or
the other so what was this come on two
thank you very much so all the
characteristics two but let's get this
by
by considering a downward gradient
flow in case you have not seen this
expression before please listen
carefully it's a a very important and
natural context uh concept essentially
you're considering water flowing down
here or if you like how the rain goes um
along the
[Applause]
surface
okay and such down down gradient
flows
fluro allow
us allow us to find
out the oil
characteristic what we mean is simply
the following kind of thing do I have
blue choke and can you see blue on the
black W I'm not
sure let's say that we put water at the
top of this sphere and imagine that the
gravity is pulling
downward then how does the water flow it
flows of course like this
right
yes naturally that's how the water flows
and then water accumulates at the bottom
so we are going to put the sink at the
bottom in other words at the top there
is a source
and at the bottom there's a sink and
everywhere else there is no more
equilibria yeah that's a perfectly
possible dynamical system or vector
field on this
manifold but you see it means that the
oila character characteristics
characteristic excuse me of S2 using
this P hope formula is equal to the sum
of the indices of this picture and well
some of the indexes
index there are only two equilibria
what's the index at the source in 2D
case plus plus one everything coming out
what's the index of a sync in two
dimensional case it's also + one for a
saddle it is minus one you remember in
2D so it's plus one + one and
miraculously comes out to be plus two
which is the answer we know to be true
from yesterday's calculation so that's
the order characteristic you see you
don't have to use this partitioning into
a network in order to discover the order
characteristic if you use this theorem
so that's one example the first example
of how information about the dynamical
system Vector field gives you a
constraint on the topology okay next
what's the simplest example that we can
imagine next a Taurus we shall put the
Taurus like this
and we'll in a moment say why we didn't
put the Taurus in horizontal Direction
but first let's discuss this tus T2 and
if we start
flowing from the top that's a
source what's going to happen well watch
closely the water that goes in this
direction keeps going keep it's going
down no problem similarly the water that
goes somewhere along here can keep going
however the water that goes in this
direction starts accumulating at this
point and in the back which I shall draw
by dotted lines you get something like
this I'm going to gesture for you to
make it even clearer and then the water
comes out of here and goes along the
inside of the Taurus
and here they
accumulate and then finally similar
picture from above there is a front flow
and back flow and everything accumulates
at the bottom which is a
sink How does it
go more
clearly can you imagine the top of the
Taurus which we are putting like this so
there's a tube like thing which we put
like this okay look at the top what we
are saying is if you flow on the side
you can just flow all the way down but
if I start flowing here you see I come
to a stop there is a point if you like
under this part the top part which is
whose tangent is horizontal so I can go
come closer and closer to this
point but if I don't come exactly along
this line of descent I can start going
down this way as well are you seeing the
picture that I'm seeing so once again
imagine a
tube which is like this okay like
that you see the tube so the top of the
tube and then if you continue there's a
bottom of the tube and then there's sort
of a hole like thing in the middle over
here okay I'm talking about what happens
at the top in this region so if I go
down this way no problem but if I come
down this
way yes there's an equilibrium
here into which you flow and in the
perpendicular Direction out which you
flow out and then you go go down and now
here when you come down there are slopes
like this coming down and then there's a
local flat part and then slopes like
this going down can you see coming down
like this and then going down like this
it's what in English we call a mountain
pass when you go over a mountain you
know you are climbing climbing climbing
you might go over a point like this but
on this side you still have high
mountain on this side you still have
Mountain that kind of geography is what
we're talking about so at that point
water is flowing in like
this but then flowing out in the
perpendicular Direction that's the
picture that we are trying to draw in
other words these points are
Subs hence the oil characteristic of
T2 is the index of the source which is+
one what are the indices of the
saddle minus one each so there are two
Saddles minus one minus one and then fin
the index of the sync at the bottom plus
one and it comes out to be
zero
we had not yesterday calculated this oil
characteristic officially but there was
a project that I
gave which explained how the oil
characteristic behaves under addition to
be precise the connected sum of
manifolds and also and the
multiplication to be precise the
cartisian or direct product of manifolds
and if you use that and use the fact
that S1 has other characteristics zero
you can easily deduce that any Taurus of
any Dimension should oil characteristic
zero also 0 * 0 * 0 always Z and bless
you whoever sneeze okay that's the
Taurus let's
then discuss
quickly a Rema surface of genus G which
is a generalization if you like of the
Taurus to higher genus you keep doing
this and as before I've decided to put
this in the upright
position okay so this is Sigma G and
they G hes the Gus is
G the
Flow by now you can imagine starts from
a source at the bottom at the top excuse
me and sink at the bottom naturally and
the way it flow flows is like this on
the side it flows in a straightforward
fashion but here you flow into the sink
into the saddle and then flow out of the
saddle
like this here you reach another
equilibrium another
sadle you go in front and you go in the
back reach the next Shadow and then you
flow sideways and so on you keep going
in the
meantime on the outside of the Taurus
where if you know this kind of thing
curvature is positive you keep just
flowing down and so you repeat this
process and eventually reach the
promised land here so you go like that
like that there's a saddle another
saddle here and water flowing
outside and this water on the outside
has been coming and finally the last
saddle ejects the water
downhill which slows into the
sink
okay thus you have all those
subs what is the O characteristic then
of Sigma G well we have one source at
the top and One Source One sink at the
bottom how many Shadows are there on
Sigma G
he 2 G as obious say yes
certainly
so there are two two G of them because
they're G holes for each hole there are
two side holes and finally there's plus
one okay what is the grand
total 2G minus 2G uh 2 minus excuse me
2G which is exactly what was announced
yesterday when we discussed the order
characteristics so you can um find out
how to calculate the topology loely
speaking from the information about
dynamical
system you can
also position the sigma
G in a different posture you don't like
standing up well lie
down let's position it like
this maybe you find it more
appealing and suppose that rain starts
falling on this what does the water flow
look like well there are
several positions at the top or maximum
points and there are several positions
at the bottom the minimum over there
those are the
sources there are now multiple sources
and those are the
sinks naturally in between what happens
well on the outside it's
easy but on the inside something
interesting happens first here there's a
behavior very similar to what happened
before you can flow down in front and in
the back if you like and then flow out
so you have a
saddle and let me denote the saddle
indicate Saddles by different colors so
I'm going to indicate Shadows by Red
because you'll see in a moment that
there are many shadows and here the
familiar style there there and there but
you see there's
more look at this
one the water can start coming in along
here
but this point is unstable in the other
direction when the water comes in like
this it can go down like this so the
water can go down here in front and in
the back and reach another s sadle here
and then from this Shadow it can go like
this or like this similarly the water
can flowing in into this
direction or into this direction and so
you have that you have many many s
here here here here and here here here
here I shall explain those new saddles
in the moment but in the meantime the
picture looks like
this you should later try to draw these
pictures yourselves and then you'll
understand better than just watching a
Japanese person draw it in front of
you usually mathematics is much easier
if you do it yourself if you watch
somebody else do it it's very very
difficult to
understand
okay a mimic for that kind of sadow
watch this
yeah in the neighborhood of this point
there are mountains coming down towards
you like this but then there are descent
directions like this so the
water rain water water comes down and
there is an equilibrium which is a
saddle into which water comes in but in
this direction it can go out so if you
look at the picture from
above you will effectively see water
coming in in this direction going out in
this direction and in between the water
is probably flowing like this and that's
exactly the picture of the
sad okay similarly here except that here
the water is coming down in this
direction along the surface and then
going down in this
direction I forgot to mention but I'd
like to point out that water is Flowing
along the surface for example you might
have been wondering well by the time
water reaches here this surface is
upside down so the water will just drop
down no please imagine that water sticks
to the surface and keeps flowing down
okay anyway so that's the
picture and so all those Reds
as
sad if you have only one color in your
Tech in your notebook you might mark
them by Cross or something like
that in this case then what is the order
characteristic of Sigma G that's again
another Sigma G is equal to well how
many sources are
there if the genus is G yes that's right
so plus
G
those are the
sources indexes of s indices of sources
how many Saddles are
there hey let's figure out the number of
sadles of this type how many 2 G because
there are G for each that two how about
Saddles of this
type two that's right 2 * G minus one
because if there G of those things the
parts in between there are only G minus
one of them so in fact what we get is
minus 2
g - 2 * Gus one those are the
Saddles and finally plus how many sinks
G also so this looks complicated and I
hope this comes out to be the same
result but is the result G + g - 2 G
that's fine and then - 2 G + 2 ah
amazingly do come out to b 2 minus 2 G
that's was
lucky th the moral of this
story is
that um all these examples all the
calculations C
culations
confirm what we found out in example 14
yesterday
directly but more
importantly you can say this is
again it tells us a way to use this pank
hope for formula yeah and it shows us a
relationship between dynamical systems
on the one hand and topology on the
other hand there's an intimate relation
relationship and this is one of those
relationships there are many many other
relationships between dynamical systems
and topology so in this particular
instance where we are going from the
left hand side to right hand
side we have some information about the
dynamical system and that gives us
information about topology okay this
kind of relationship symbiosis as some
people like to call happens quite often
in mathematics there are connections
between different fields
and you can translate one field Pro
problems in one field into another or
you can use information from one field
to solve problems in another field and
so
on
okay good let's continue then um with
the discussion a little more theoretical
of how the left hand side can help the
right hand
side there is a theorem coming up but
before then I'd like to prepare a LMA
which which is rather important LMA
17 the LMA says do you know what the LMA
is LMA is a small theorem but which is
used as an auxiliary auxiliary or
stepping stone or preparation for the
main result okay LMA um if m is closed
and of course
orientable you remember why we keep
saying closed no boundary because we are
using the intersection theory in the
background okay okay if it is closed and
if the dimension of let's say m is
odd then the sum of the indices of any
Vector field the at X for X running over
all the
equilibrium B is equal
to
zero for
all Vector field field V on
N we shall prove this result by a direct
picture concerning the intersection
theory note that the the result is
rather spectacular we are saying that
the this sum complicate sum comes out to
be exactly zero we already have one
example of a Taurus but in the case of
Taurus it came out to be zero for a
different reason from this reason here
the key assumption is that the dimension
of the manifold is OD so what is a more
appropriate example it's the example of
S1 for example you remember that for S1
the oil characteris was Zero in general
for S OD the O characteristic was always
zero and this is a general thing behind
all those patterns that we have been
noticing
yesterday the
proof is by a deformation argument so I
shall begin the proof here and go on
there
let's deform this given Vector field
whatever it
is V to the another Vector field which
is the everywhere zero Vector field you
remember
this strange Vector
field and vice
versa such a thing was called the zero
section if you
remember and the picture is as
follows you have M and you might have
two colors would be
helpful
one
two you might
have the vector field represented by the
section gamma V and the other zero
section every zero Vector field is
simply identifiable with M itself so
this is a gamma of zero see it's a
vector fi that takes the value zero at
all points the zero section and what I
mean by the form one to the other means
that I going to take at each point the
value of this Vector field and then just
move it to zero or move it up so I'm
going in between like this if you at
equilibria where it's zero to begin with
so I'm not going to do the
deformation okay so this is what time
do that's the picture in the tangent
bundle if you want a picture on M itself
this is a digression we are saying that
at each point there is a value of V
whatever it is at this point and I
direct deform it to
the zero Vector at this point what do I
do I just start shrinking it that's all
I do and it's shrinking is a continuous
process continuous deformation so we can
use the deformation Theory so in
particular what we are doing is um here
the deformation which is s of I think
gamma 0 + 1 - s of gamma V would be a
good deformation um Family between s
goes from 0 to one you see when s is
zero you get just gamma V and when s is
one you get just gamma Z and it's in
between this is the interpolation if you
like between V and zero
okay and then what you get is the
following let's calculate the
intersection number between the zero
section and the graph of
gamma okay that number I'd like to
remind you is exactly the sum of the
indices of V at
X because what are X these are the
equilibria of v in other words it's at
those points you see and that's where
the two graphs intersect and we're
saying that at each of these
intersections you take plus or minus one
according to the orientations so the
intersection number gamma 0 and Gamma V
is exactly equal to the sum of indices
at the equilibria we so we are
calculating this
number well this is equal to well look
zero can be deformed to V and V can be
deformed to zero and we saw that the
inter section number does not depend on
the deformation you can just deform one
vector field into another Vector field
and it's always the same so we can also
write it as gamma V intersect number
gamma 0 that's confusing but I hope you
can see what it is so zero has been
deformed to v v has been deformed zero
and in the course of this deformation
the intersection number is invariant
intersection number is isotopy invariant
so that's uh true this is by theorem 10
of this SE of this
chapter yeah
and since gamma 0 is always isotopic to
gamma V inside
the tent
by okay so that's
true on the other hand this
number let's swap the
factors around so instead of gamma V
intersect gamma 0 let's write it as
gamma 0 intersect GMA
V what happens when we swap the sub
manifolds to the intersection number
well you have to put
the some sign in front do you remember
so in the most primitive case that we
studied last week we are studying the
intersection number between two
manifolds k and l to many FS inside some
ambient space and so the intersection
number of K and L was related to the
intersection number of L and K you
exchange the order there's a
relationship and the relationship was a
difference in sign what was the
difference in sign it's minus one to do
you remember
the it is the dimension of this times
the dimension of this okay but what is
the dimension of this times the
dimension of this both have Dimension
M so it is dimension of M
squ but you
know dimension of M if it's
even it square is also
even dimension of M if it's odd it
square is also
odd is that okay so dimension of
m² and dimension of
M have what's the expression the same
parity evenness or oddness do you know
the word
parity parity evenness orness parity so
it shows that if the dimension of M is
odd this becomes minus one but look
gamma 0 intersect number gamma V equal
min-1 GMA 0 intercept GMA V what can
this be it must be zero because because
it's equal it's all negative and hence
the
result is that okay I hope it's not too
quick in contrast if the dimension of M
is even you get the plus sign in front
so you can't say anything this gives you
no information it it's just saying that
something is equal itself well of course
but when the dimension is OD you can get
the result that something is equal it's
negative so that something was zero to
begin with and
proof okay that's a standard technique
in mathematics by the way one of the
many standard techniques in order to
show that something zero you show that
it is equal to its own negative and we
could do this thanks to the isotopy inv
variance under the um of the
intersection
number okay I should probably quote
where that um formula comes from so this
excuse me um is by chapter three that
last chapter and this exchange of
science theorum was um proved in theum
okay well after that
LMA it's immediately obvious what we can
do next we have this pank hop from last
uh from yesterday that the number of sum
of indices is equal to the oil
characteristic so an immediate
consequence of that LMA theum 18 is that
for
every closed and of course orientable
manifold sometimes I forget to say
orientable but please assume Orient
every orientable
manifold
M of all the
dimension key assumption we have that
the oila characteristic must b
z and the proof is simply a combination
of
dmma 17 and the previous theorem that's
the o p hope theorem
good this is equal to the order
characteristic so order characteristic
is zero that's that's what we're
saying okay and this theorem that we
have just proved
generalizes a lot of the information
that we already know in particular the
information
that the or characteristic of all
dimensional spheres are all zero yeah
all dimensional spheres are all Compact
and excuse me Clos and orientable so
they have
um what characteristics
here